My my teacher used to say, "When you go
to the dollar store, take $100."
Okay? Like, okay, you're not going to
spend more than $25 at the dollar store,
but when you go, you should you should
have $100.
It means uh when you're trying to help
people, which is what we do,
when you're trying to serve people,
which is what we do, then you should
have a big tool bar. Okay. You should
have many tools to help other people
and um in my life I tried to give you
more and more tools that you can use and
some of them you use every day like
pliers
and some of them you rarely use like uh
random mallets, right? Disump.
Uh
but every tool has its place and every
tool has its time and the more tools I
can give you to put in your box uh the
more you can serve other people. So to
my proposal tonight in the time which is
okay.
Uh do you mind if I just go straight
through to eight? Is that okay? It's
seven now. You're halfway there. How's
your bladder? It's okay. Okay. Uh
If you if you have a problem just feel
welcome to
um
so tonight we'll start a completely new
subject.
So you have done some some of you have
been here for 20 years or more.
Uh you have completed the Gishi course
the basic text of the Gishi course the
five grade books in the sevenyear
program in New York.
Some of you have completed the 7-year
advanced Buddhism course here that was
held here. Um, many of you have attended
the 14 years of the
class, Minka class,
uh, which began in 200
three
and we are now one quarter of the way
through the text. We're still going.
Uh
and then many of you have been attending
the long run course which will take for
12 or 14 years and we have finished 3
years and you dandelion sports have to
catch up on that. Okay. Especially
nowador has to translate another
thousand pages into Hebrew. Uh, by the
way, the work that the uh Israeli team
did on the hypertext was extremely
helpful at Google and I'd like to thank
them for that.
They're like, "Okay, we understand
English and the Tibetan, but what's this
other thing?" I said, "That's Hebrew."
They were very cool. So uh I hope the
Israeli team
can help a lot in the hyper testing for
that project. Okay. I hope Loro will
give us some man power like your people
like that. Okay. Cuz it it was very very
helpful. They were very excited about
what the work that you did. Okay. Uh so
I thought tonight uh since we don't have
enough projects going on
that we could start a new project uh
which is called Abida. Okay
and there are four great schools
of ancient India and Abid Dharma is one
of them.
I have a a vision which I'd like to
share with you. uh there are many
subjects which I was trained in because
I was in the right place at the right
time as Dr. John would say
uh I was uh I was there the day that
that the Tibet started coming out into
the world. I was there and I met the
greatest and I lived with him for 25
years and he he taught me constantly for
free and uh
I I would like to pass on what I learned
and there are many many things I haven't
taught you. There are there are decades
of things I haven't taught you and u
I would like to teach there. So we have
an idea to sort of divorce the academic
uh subjects from the retreat
area. So we feel that D mountain is has
strength in long-term retreats, deep
retreats. So people from all over the
world will be coming here uh to do deep
retreats and we will keep the cabins
filled uh with people from many many
countries who want to do they want to
learn the experience of going inside and
finding higher truth inside which can
only be done with deep dream. I just
went to uh the Christian church where I
grew up and uh it's uh it's Lenton time
right
and they are talking on the subject of
uh
Jesus's time in the desert the 40 days
in the desert and it was very pleasant
for me to sit and listen to this sermon
about why going to the desert alone
would enlighten you you know and it was
very beautiful. It's very wonderful. The
priest was defending this practice
uh that Jesus did. And um
I think it's extremely important. I
don't think you can really
find out who you are if you don't learn
to do retreat. So this place has two
functions in memory. One is to provide
the logistical
place to do retreat because you can't
get those places.
They cost thousands of dollars. Uh,
no one's going to crazy enough to give
you a three-ear retreat for free. And no
one's crazy enough to build the cabin
and leave it there for somebody else and
waste all their money.
Uh,
first is to have the place, right? And
then you have to train people who come.
People are going to show up and say, I
want to do, can I do one of those dream
retreats? And you're like, have you ever
done a dream? No. Do you know anything
about train? No.
But I'll sit there and then you're like,
"No, these people were trained for seven
years. These people did seven years of
training to go into retreat." So I see
Diamond Mountain as a place where
people from all over the world can learn
to do retreat. They get training in even
a three-day retreat or a 5day retreat or
a 10day retreat. They get trained on
what the heck to do after they close the
door.
you know
uh and then we have the facility. So I
see that as long and then I would like
to take the academic uh subjects
the what do you call it the training
in the classics
uh we we probably we are looking at some
buildings in Sudon
and that's more viable for people who
want to be a student there you can get
work there a lot of our students are
working there already
and it's a beautiful beautiful
environment it's a beautiful place and
so My dream is to
sort of have a college,
teachers college in Sedona for the for
the what do you call
academic subjects
and then mountain will be mainly for
retreat
and uh
I have several goals there. One is that
I would like to pass on everything I've
learned which would take a a long time
and it has to be close to my home
uh because my home is where my teacher
is and I have to be close to my teacher.
So um
so that's like a we could do that for 10
20 30 years depending on how long the
machine lasts but we have to record
things and we have to pass on those
uh
I would like to train DCI teachers there
from all over the world. Uh I would like
to train ACI teachers there from all
over the world. And this is Mr. W's idea
actually we were talking in Shin
and he said you know we should start a
place in America to train people and
so he's been very kind to help me
understand how how we could grow
what we do and so I'd like I would like
to have place for VIPs to come from
other countries
and get training and then I think um we
could help support that college by
offering training for
American and Western
executives who would like to do business
in in China or Singapore or Taiwan. We
have the staff.
Uh we have a large in Singapore alone we
have 60 volunteers. Uh in uh China we
have many we are in many cities in China
and we have many many volunteers.
Uh we have a great staff and we can help
American
and and western business people to learn
Chinese culture, some Chinese language,
how to conduct yourself in China, how to
do business because in the future the
big
cooperation will be between east and
west. It will be between Asia and
and North America. So if we can help
people to do that, it will also make
more international cooperation and much
less likely for any kind of conflict.
If many Chinese friends are here and if
many American friends are there, then it
will help reduce the risk of conflict in
the world. Otherwise, there may be
conflict. And uh so I feel like we could
play a large role in that. And I'm
hoping people like Mr. room
could come and teach there, help us
start and and then teach us teach
western people how to
do business there and then we could
train each other. We could train each
other and uh I think it would change the
world. I think we can help the whole
world if we have a place. So that's my
dream
another dream. Okay. All right. So uh
there are many many subjects to cover
that I've never taught you.
Uh one of the most important is called
Abid Dharma.
I was thinking a lot about Amid Dharma
because I when I went to China
to a place called
I asked Mr. would teach me something
and he said I have this book it's by
someone named
[Music]
and uh it's called like the hund doors
of the dharma and this is one of the
texts that Mr. who specializes in
that book by Masabandu it came to Tibet
but from China because the Indian copies
were lost so some of the kir interior
were completed in Tibet from China and
this one book by master Gasabandu which
Mr. who specializes in uh was lost in
India and uh it survived in China and
then it was translated about
800 years ago into Japan. Uh and it's
part of our tenure. It's part of our
kind. So he was teaching me master and I
was like getting excited and then I
thought well I should
I kind of made a commitment to my
teacher K to to translate Abu Dharma
Kosha. This is the root book on Abid. He
taught it to me for 12 years. The story
goes like this and you should know on
the first night of 15 years of work or
so you should know the story. Okay. So
he uh I had just reached his uh house. I
was uh 21 or two. I don't remember.
I don't even remember being that age. Uh
right except for certain major events
with high school girlfriends and stuff.
Um and uh
and he said, "We're going down to
Washington DC." And I said, "Okay,
whatever you want, mama." And he said,
"You're going to be my assistant." You
know, I said, "What are we going to do?"
He says, "You're going to drive me to
school every day cuz I'm going to learn
English at Georgetown University."
Someone paid for him
and then in the evening I'm going to
teach, you know, and I said, "Well, what
are you going to teach?" He said, "Well,
I have a group there, but I'm also going
to teach a professor from
American University
uh who wants to translate the kosha
in the commentary by the first
who who was Jessa student
and uh so I he spent many sessions with
this professor whose name I won't
mention
and uh I said, "Can I just sit in on
since I'm the driver,
you know, and I might as well just sit
there and can I
can I sit there? And he said, "Yeah, you
can sit there, but you have to memorize
the root text.
This is hundreds of pages." Uh, so I
started and I didn't know what it meant.
I didn't know Tibetan, but I started
memorizing it. I got through uh three
and a half chapters.
It took 12 years. and uh he taught then
the guy dropped out the professor
decided he was too busy or crazy guy
and then I'm like let me finish it you
know let me finish the translation so
he's like okay let's keep going you know
and it took 12 years
and he taught me I'll be d for 12 years
and uh we did a translation
and then uh
it's still there it was my first
translation I threw threw it out later
and I did it again and then I I'm
throwing that out and I'm doing it again
now. Uh now John Brady and Dan Styver
uh did a 14-year project in St.
Petersburg to save
141,000 Tibetan manuscripts.
And in there are the missing textbooks
of my monetary survey from the 1600s.
uh by Chioma Dr. Shin and um Jim has
translated
two of his commentaries. He wrote a
commentary on Shinjin and he wrote a
commentary on
she's translated them into English.
Somebody has to help me translate it
into Chinese
or publish it in Sanskrit in English and
Chinese. The three are finished. The
three languages are finished, but we're
missing the Chinese.
So, Chony Lama is an extraordinary llama
born in 1675.
He attended the greatest Buddhist
monastery.
He wrote the textbooks. He wrote he
wrote many of the textbooks and you have
studied him many times. Those of you who
studied the ACI 18 courses, he he he
figures heavily in the sixth course
because he wrote the commentary to the D
and in the advanced teachings you had
him many times. For example, in the
commentaries on he taught uh we used his
commentaries on he's extraordinarily
clear and extraordinarily methodical
uh almost like no other Tibetan in
history and
so with I did the first dynamics
commentary it's about 400 pages but I
would like I propose and actually you
don't have a choice
uh I propose to do chon
commentary to the cuz it's it's more
organized and it's more clear and it's
it's it's more helpful. Okay. And uh so
the other translation is there but I I
would like to do this one and uh in
order to fulfill my teacher's wishes
because Kench wanted
my commentary in the world.
So
I'm doing it for him because he loves me
too.
Okay. So, it took a while,
but it's an extraordinary conference.
Okay.
So, we'll just keep doing that,
especially in our new college in Sedona
if we get it. Okay. Uh here we go.
You have a text
and we'll just start. And it's really
just this weekend is just a teaser.
Okay. It's like you go to the restaurant
and they give you those free little
dessert bites and your homie will order
it later.
So, we're just starting. Uh, just get
used to it. Just dip your toe into
Abidor. Okay?
So, there are four great schools of
Buddhism in India and there are four
great schools of Buddhism in Tibetan.
They are completely separate from each
other. Okay? They're different things.
Uh in India
there were four great schools of thought
developed. Uh they were all taught by
Lord of Buddha and then he taught
philosophy in four different and
sometimes
contradictory ways. Okay. uh Lord Buddha
when he was speaking to
people in the impoverished areas of
Buenoseris he taught it one way and then
when he got to Don he taught it in a
different way and then people were like
later they found the two books and they
didn't match up
and people got worried you know Buddha
taught on four vastly speaking four
different levels in ancient India one is
the
the the first one the foundational one
which sometimes we call lowest but I
don't think so the foundation of all
Buddhist
study was okay so even in the time of
lord Buddha
uh some of his disciples like katyana
uh took his teachings and organized them
into seven great books called abidama
okay there used to be uh seven great
books of Abida and some of them we still
study some of them still exist but not
much
and they are like encyclopedias
of Buddhist knowledge
that Lord Buddha left that were
assembled after he passed from this
world okay so Abid Dharma is the
foundation of all Buddhist practice and
it's the earliest teaching of Lord
Buddha so it was organized
um in the first 2 century uh ad okay in
India
uh
after that came the
South
which are kind of the schools the school
which deals with perceptual theory and
formal reasoning like uh mainly when I
look at a car and I see four black round
things and a couple of long silver
things how do I know it's a car
Why do I see it as a car?
By the way, the the challenge with all
these ancient philosophies is how do you
use them
when you're teaching? I saw John even
talk to the largest home
construction company in Arizona and it
was very interesting. How do you take
this knowledge and help people be more
successful in their real life, people in
the family life? How do you how do you
make them more successful
in their day-to-day relationships?
So the
the second school the second grade
school in India was called South
Trantica and they were thinking how how
is it that you recognize things because
you could manipulate that and learn to
recognize the world in a different way
and maybe it would be better and maybe
there wouldn't be war or hunger. You see
that's the idea. The third school is
my yoga or chittra
and Mr. Woo is also a master of this
school.
Mr. Woo is a master of the Aid Dharma
school taught by the school
which is very sexy but we can talk about
it. So uh there are there's a text by
that that teaches that. Okay. Uh and
then uh the fourth goal
middle way okay which is the foundation
of our current practice. It it is the
correct explanation of of reality and
it's what we use in the higher
teachings. It's the foundation of the
higher teachings. The seven-year program
here from 2003 to 2010 or whatever was
founded on uh the middle school which is
which is our basic we call loop what's
our position
it's it's our positions it's the our
native position it's what we believe
okay then why don't we study the three
lush
huh to flush out wrong ideas in our own
mind
yeah flush out wrong ideas in our own
mind like a good answer nice answer. Uh
the lower schools represent the wrong
ideas that would pop into a person's
mind automatically, including me.
Okay? So, we have to study them to study
and then we have to study the
differences between that school and what
we're being taught in the middle age.
Okay? And the differences tell
everything. Okay? It's as if it's a very
common pedagogical or educational method
in in Asia.
that you teach somebody first
what's wrong. You teach them a wrong
system and then you correct it. And in
the process of correction, they learn.
You see, so you tell somebody emptiness
means everything changes.
And then later you tell them that's not
what emptiness means at all. And then
you're like, well, why did you tell me
before was everything changed? And then
it makes you think and that's the object
of education. So education in Asia is
different than a western education. It
has a different methodology. Okay. So
we're going to go see the Abi Dharma
which is the foundation of all Buddhist
schools. Okay. And it's beautiful and
it's fantastic. Okay. It's
extraordinary. So I'm just going to jump
into the text. I could give you a
lecture on the the eight chapters and
its structure. How the third chapter
presents the world down to subatomic
particles and up to light years. have
that describes the end of this world
when the sun supernovas and how it was
created by cosmic dust clouds
written 17 centuries ago but I'm not
going to do that or the questions about
the nature of time four positions on the
nature of time
uh we're not going to do that tonight
I'm not going to talk about it the
fourth chapter I could tell you is the
greatest presentation of karma in all
Buddhist literature
and it's the basis of most of DC
but we don't have time to do all that
I'm not going to go through all that
okay
and the fifth chapter
the greatest presentation of mental
affliction
addiction you can say
and then the other chapters the greatest
pres the practice of watching your
breath
the practice of basic meditations all
the basic meditations of Buddhism are
found in a kosha They all come together.
Okay. So, I'm not gonna give you a whole
outline and the whole I'm just gonna
start with the text and let him do it.
Okay. All right. And
you know, if you sign up, it's going to
be 15 years or so. Okay. I'm just
warning you now.
And if we can have a place in Sedona, it
would be nice because we can also stream
it live. And if you're in Tel Aviv or if
you're in Gualahara
or if you're in Sophia
or Beijing, you can watch it live
because we cannot get internet strength
here. We we've been Scott's been working
with the phone company all week,
offering them any amount of money and
and anything they want. And they said,
"We just can't do it." You know, they
put in a Nazi signal here and that's all
they can do.
So I think if we have Sudona we we would
like to uh webcast all of these
teachings and then people all over the
world can can learn them and there are
we have simultaneous translation into
many languages
in Mexico it's simultaneous translation
into Spanish and in China simultaneously
into Chinese and other countries
which leads me to I would like to thank
a person uh who's been one of my three
assistants in China and one of my three
translators there and she's been kind
enough to make the trip uh from Beijing
with Mr. W uh and her name is shopping
and she's really responsible for me
meeting this. So that's another story.
Uh so you should thank her first. Okay.
Let's
so that I I would like to video
everything. I would like to translate
everything and I would like to offer it
live free live webcast. Okay. And then
we finish all these subjects and then I
can go back to my ro
without feeling guilty. Okay. All right.
Let's start.
I'm teaching this the old way. If you
don't like that, I don't care. Uh we're
going to do every single word. Uh
we're going to go the old way. And uh
I'm not going to make it easy and I'm
not going to water it down. And we're
just going to go straight to the real
thing. I'm not going to make it simple.
Okay? And uh the first night will be
okay. It's like the first 15 minutes of
yoga class.
And then later we get to the real stuff.
Okay, here we go.
Say cha. Say ch
[Music]
So the pronunciation as you're gathering
it doesn't match the letters because
Tibetan has a lot of strange
pronunciation. These are the correct
letters for the pronunciations, but
we'll teach it to you some other time.
Just be glad I didn't put it in Tibetan
script. Okay? Say
cha.
So there are a lot of silent prefix
letters. If you hear something and
there's an M in front of it, just ignore
it. Ch means what?
Yeah. What's mean?
Start dictionary entry. What's that
mean?
Start dictionary entry within me.
We're making a video of dictionary
event.
So every time I get to a hard word, I I
tell them start dictionary entry and
then Adam cuts it out out of the video
and we put it on YouTube for free. And
if you don't know what ch means, you
just type chos into YouTube and you get
me explaining it tonight. Okay, you
ready? Start dictionary entry. Ch. Say
chair.
Chair is the Tibetan word, a translation
of the word dharma. Okay. In in
Sanskrit. Okay.
And there's a definition of the word
dharma in Tibetan. It's sayi.
So that's a that's a literal explanation
from the ancient Sanskrit because the
word Zin the Sanskrit root for the word
Zin which means to hold the Sanskrit
root is
dur say D.
So the root is so it's a pun the
definition is a pun because you
is called
okay all Sanskrit words are derived from
800 roots. If you if you memorize
800 words in Sanskrit, you can pretty
much figure out any Sanskrit word. I did
it on the bus from New Jersey to New
York. It takes about I don't know six
months.
You can memorize all the roots of
Sanskrit and then you can
then you can read it almost. Okay. So D
is is the root. Dharma is the is the
word that came from it. The noun. Okay.
Meaning that thing which holds
what's
which holds its own essence. Anything
which
possesses or contains or holds its own
essence is a
dharma is the definition of dharma. So
dharma really means things
any any event any thing in the world in
the universe is called the eight a
dharma. Okay. A dharma. All right. Then
later the explanation of those dharmas
came to be called the
dharma. Okay. And then you know nowadays
dharma means dharma teaching teaching
the dharma things like that. Okay.
Uh and that's the meaning of the word
dharma. So here it means
knowledge. Here it means knowledge.
Okay. Uh stop dictionary entry for ch uh
chumba. Mumba is the Tibetan translation
of ai. AP. Okay. Alpi came into English
as EP like epicenter. Apple G like if
you fly your F-14 to 58,000 ft Mac 1.57
over Pensacola
then uh you are reaching apogee or
something I think and uh the the word
apple comes from Abi. So Abi Dharma
means highest.
Okay.
Highest. So I've translated as higher
knowledge. Okay, Abid Dharma you can
think of as higher knowledge and he will
spend a lot of pages on explaining the
meaning of abidha. Okay, we'll get
there. I'm just telling you the title of
the book. We'll be lucky if we finish
the title of the book. That's okay.
Okay, say
this is a lone word from Sanskrit. It's
not Tibetan. Yeah. Chika
is an ancient uh Indian word, Sanskrit
word for commentary. It means a
commentary. Okay.
Sometimes the Tibetan is well
abbreviated to tick start dictionary
entry. uh tick which you see here which
is a retroflex t with a t with a long i
e ka cha say cha
curl your tongue back retroflex your
tongue
cha so that's if most uh words in
Sanskrit that have retroflex in such a
position are often older
than than Sanskrit. Okay, they are the
original language before the Arians came
to India. Okay, 5,000 years ago. So So
these are mostly southern language,
southern Indian. They were pushed
Dervidian race was pushed into southern
India by the invaders from the north
uh which are the classical Indian
culture and the audience. Okay. So
that's
when you see something like tikka, it's
probably older. Okay. Uh so ticker means
commentary. All right.
And the Tibetans will often shorten it
to tick say.
So sometimes this commentary will be
will be called.
This means an abid commentary
commentary. Okay. Got it. And dictionary
entry for tick. All right. Sometimes by
the way, open it up again. Sometimes
they don't make the the uh vowel long so
they'll just say tick and then you'll
get confused. So be aware. Okay.
You know
is one of our nuns. Okay. Who's going to
be running this place after she's done
her other stuff helping with one of the
dirty work.
Yeah. Yeah. Never mind. Never mind.
No, I I heard you were going to help
out, but I we'll talk about it. Sorry, I
didn't mean to address it. Galce means
uh Gals means son or daughter of the
victorious ones, and she's just a
daughter. And uh it means uh it means
what's a word for it?
Bodhisatta. It's a it's a synonym for
bodhisat.
Okay. Uh so here gawa means here it
means gawa j means along with along with
and unfortunately it comes after the
second party
start dictionary entry jasa j b c a s it
means along with but if you're going to
say the victorious Buddhists along with
their daughter daughter daughter
daughters you would say victorious
Buddhist daughters J And it comes at the
end. Okay. Uh stop dictionary entry for
chain. Okay. Uh gaga means the Buddhist
and their bodhicas. Okay. They're
bodhicappa kids. Like if you dance and
you have Doras and you have like 500
kids, you know they would be the same.
They are the same. They are the
princesses.
Okay. Y
park is short for papa.
Arya.
Arya meaning someone who has seen
emptiness directly. Unfortunately,
Hitler got a a hold of the word and used
it for what we call evil purposes
and that's just you know unfortunate but
it's a very beautiful word in Sanskrit
art. It means someone who has seen
emptiness therapy. So papa is the
Tibetan fork
or
collection
collection or big group. Okay. Park
means all those guys that they areas.
Okay. Probably shouldn't translate his
word here. Park
all of them. Gongun means what did they
really have in their heart? What did
they really mean when they talked? What
was their true intention? Means true
intention. Okay. What what was their
secret
thought that they were trying to
communicate? Okay. Uh,
by the way, I will stop by 9, so half.
Don't worry. 20 more minutes. Hang in
there. You had a long day out in the hot
sun. The retreat retreats all have
migraines cuz that's what happens on the
first day out of three retreat.
And you can go home and be miserable.
Okay.
Means it illuminates. You know the word
light,
clear light, right? So sa is the verb to
to illuminate what it's this is this
book is a
son. So he's he says my book is is the
sun
and it's going to illuminate
uh what the Buddhist and the bhistas and
all that big bunch of realized beings
what they had in mind. I'm going to
illuminate it for you not with a
flashlight but with the sun with the
power of the sun. Okay? It's like I'm
not just shedding some light on this
subject. I am they sometimes they call
ninj I am the day maker. I am day maker.
I'm making I'm I'm illuminating the
planet
and I'm I'm illuminating their inner
thought with the sun of my book. So the
book is called the light of the sun.
Okay.
And it's a commentary on we didn't do
say
is a translation of the Sanskrit word
kosha. Okay. Say kosha.
You see kosha spelled either with a
retroflex sha or without a retroflex
shot. It's an acceptable variant called
duma. Okay. Say kosha. Then tongue your
turn your tongue back and gosh.
So if you want to impress somebody in
India you say I'm studying a dharma cor.
Wow your accent is perfect.
Say don't say okay it's
yeah then you're very impressive.
Kosha means uh
it's either it's a treasure
or it's a treasure chest. Okay, we'll
talk about it later. It's either a
treasure or a treasure chest. Okay, I
have friends named you know they they
are a accounting class of kings
from ancient India who live around
Bombay and they're big in the diamond
business now. So anyway, kosher means
kosher means
treasure or treasure or treasure. Okay,
we'll talk about it. So this book is
called the treasure. It's a commentary
on the treasure house of higher
knowledge which was written by
1700 years ago. Okay, 17 centuries ago.
Very beautiful book.
I'll tell you a little bit about Vasandu
tomorrow. Most of us know he's the half
brother of
who wrote who wrote the Aid Dharma book
according to the mindbuilding school
which Mr. W is teaching so well.
Okay.
So we always start out with a
the writer will always start out with a
an obesence. Uh they will bow down to
some holy being or to some holy thing.
And this is a tradition in ancient
India. Okay. And it's often given in the
Sanskrit language. Okay. So what we have
left is Sanskrit in Tibetan letters.
Okay. So please say
not. Okay. That's a different word.
That's a long story. I will do it.
plural dative in Sanskrit.
Okay, no problem. Dual dual. Yeah, I
think so. I bow down to these two. Okay.
Uh what? Buddhas and body and guru.
Uh guru meaning what?
What's the Yeah. What's the for guru?
And it's like these demons. There are
these demons. uh
have gotten a hold of some things like
tantra or guru and they say oh this is a
dirty thing you know gurus are dirty
guru means like a bad person cult leader
guru and uh it's a very it's a very sad
and terrible thing guru is very holy
beautiful pure it means uh your heart
teacher who guides you through this life
and past death,
you know, and and it's a very very
beautiful word. It comes from a root
that means heavy or weighty and the word
gravity comes from it. Okay. So guru is
a very beautiful very very beautiful
stunning angelic pure crystallin happy
joyful being who guides you. Yeah. And
then it got all corrupted in by
somebody. These are like demonic in my
in my opinion. They take those words and
make them they make them dirty, you
know. But that seems to be some people's
business. Okay. Say guru.
Okay. Uh Buddha.
So I bow down. The author is bound down
to
his teacher,
the Buddhist and the Buddhist. Okay.
All right. Next. Oh, by the way, it's a
question for you. Why did he put teacher
first?
Here's a long story. We've been studying
it for like a year but uh in alarm
course but basically
there can be lots of Buddhist body in
the universe but they cannot speak to
you because you cannot see them because
your karma is not good enough. So as in
the case of Jesus Christ
uh the the divine will take a human form
and and communicate to to us to normal
people in a human form
and so in a way they are more kind and
more important for us. They are our uh
USB cable to the real thing you know. So
if you say what's more important the USB
cable or you know you say I want the
cable just give me the cable cuz I don't
care how powerful the thing is if I
don't have the cable I can't use it.
You see what I mean? So the guru becomes
more important than the human
than the machine. You see what I mean?
Uh so for us, for us normal people, a
human being who can come down to our
level and looks like us and act like us,
uh we can relate to them and they are
more valuable for our life purposes than
these uh ethereal divine beings that we
can't contact. Okay, cool. They are the
internet Wi-Fi.
Then the Buddhas are the internet. Okay.
All right, here we go.
Uh, now he's gonna do and I still have
you for 10 more minutes. So, just look
cheerful
cuz I'm going to use the time. I don't
care
cuz I love it and it's so helpful and it
will help you so much and you can help
other people. It's another nice little
wrench in your toolkit called Abida.
Okay.
Okay, he's making poetry. These are his
opening poems. All right, here we go.
Means the three what?
No, no count. Count countless.
Okay, countless three.
This refers to the time it takes to
become a Buddha if you don't study
tantra. And tantra is also not a dirty
word. It's a beautiful, high, pure,
moral, ethical, clean, compassionate,
tappy, wonderful thing. And I don't know
how the
inquirer got hold of it, but don't just
trust me, okay? It's a beautiful it's
based on very pure moral behavior and
it's a wonderful
teachings to contact angelic beings and
very sweet. Uh anyway, if you don't
practice that, if you just do the
normal, what do you call?
If you do economy class and not business
class,
uh
then it will take Chang soon to become a
a ch means countless eons.
Three countless eons. So it seems like a
contradiction to say
three countless.
So in in abi
kosha
in the abidama teachings not in the
kosha actually there are
each number up to the each power of 10
up to 10 to the 60th power has a
separate name
like that each Each each order of 10 has
its own name. Okay? So 10 to the 60th
power is the last one. They only go up
to 10 with 60 zeros after that. And
people memorize these things. I didn't I
only got up to the sixth one.
The 10 to the 60th power is called turn.
Okay? It's called innumerable. But it
refers to a certain number. You figure
out how many billions. David stuff will
tell me in about six minutes.
How many millions that is just like
million million million million. You can
figure it out. You have you now you have
five millions. Uh
so uh three of three three * 10 the 60th
power eons each eon is many millions of
years. Okay.
Just doing nice things for the people
and trying to be a nice person.
You can become a Buddha but it will take
that many years.
Who did it? Lord Buddha did it. Okay.
You collected the two collections.
Basically, the karma which created your
body and the karma which created the
mind of a Buddha is called the two
collection.
When we finish the class, we say
you're hoping, right? People salivate
when they hear
Right.
That's those are code words for the
karma that creates our Buddhist body and
the karma that creates a Buddhist mind
are called. So you collected the SNI for
three countless eels. Who
teacher
the Lord Buddha? So Lord Buddha in
Buddhism is sometimes just like you New
Yorkers, you arrogant New Yorkers.
Where do you live? The city
of city people are the same. Where do
you live? Mex
one day I asked this guy. He came to my
class in Colorado said where you from?
He said I said I know but where you
from? No, I'm from Mexico. I said, but
what's that mean? Mexico City. Sweet.
Oh, yeah. Okay. Okay. They they think
there.
So, teacher is what we call Buddhist
call the Buddha. Okay. All right. You're
not really arrogant, New York. You just
make sure.
Nobody's arrogant when you have those
kind of beards. Okay. All right.
Okay. So,
you completed the the two collections.
You completed completed all the karma
you needed to have a Buddhist body
and you reached the kusu.
The three holy bodies of Buddha
means uh that state of the three holy
bodies that supreme state means you
reach it. Okay.
Uh
so three he's playing on trees here.
Each line if you notice has at least two
sums in it. Check it out.
How many gsum in there? How many is it?
Is it eight?
Somebody count them up quickly.
Yeah. Has two threes in it. He's playing
he's playing game. He wants to he's
showing off how well he can write. Okay.
So,
we had we already had two threes. What
was the first one?
What was the second one?
Now we have Rick Jensen. Say
Rick Jen.
Rick Jensen.
Rick Jensen means three levels of
disciples, three levels of students.
Okay.
We can say what?
And uh
is means what?
Listener track. Listener track. Okay.
Self-made Buddha track. And then Chu
Simba
Chen Mahayana track. So there are three
tracks. You can go through your Buddhist
career to Nirvana or enlightenment on
one of three tracks depending on how
smart you are. Smart meaning spiritually
smart meaning kind and compassionate and
caring. Okay? If you're really caring,
if you're spiritually sharp, you get to
go to Buddhisoft track.
And if you're a little lower, you go to
what's called the self-made Buddha
track, which are not self-made
Buddhists. That's another story. And
then if you're lower than that, you can
go to listener track. But
dja, what's dulja?
Disciple.
Huh?
Good. Great. Dulja means the word dulja
is the Tibetan word for disciple or
student. Okay.
But I like the derivation of the word. J
means future participle. To be blanked.
To be blanked. Dul means broken
like a horse like a wild horse. Okay.
The word in Tibetan for a disciple is
that which is to be broken like a wild
horse. It doesn't mean broken like a you
know smash them. It means like a wild
horse and you jump on them and they jump
around and then you
what do you tame them? Women say tame.
Okay.
The word disciple probably is the same,
right? They are to be disciplined. Okay.
Uh anyway, doja means
we are like wild animals when we meet
our teacher. Dharmically, spiritually we
are like wild animals. We are like
little things that bite.
And am I kidding? A person who has not
been trained in spiritual things is like
a little thing that bites and then the
teacher tra. The teacher makes you soft
and gentle and kind. Okay, that's the
goal. Your job. You are someone who is
to be broken
and I was broken very well by my teacher
as John knows.
Okay.
So to all those disciples
means you turn the wheel of the dharma.
You turn the wheel of the dharma very
well. R means very well. Raar how many
wheels?
Three wheels. Okay. So Lord Buddha in
his lifetime had three specific periods
of his teaching career. Okay. His
teaching mission was carried out in
three grand stages. Okay. The first was
first turning of the wheel started at
Dear in Sasi. Okay. and started to teach
started to teach people. The the main
thing in our tradition in our media
tradition that that distinguishes the
first turn of the wheel is what Lord
Buddha said things
come from your own side everything.
Okay. Where's that? Who's got it? I need
it. Let's go. Let's go.
So in the first turning of the wheel,
Lord Buddha said, The pen is coming from
its own side. You are watching the pen.
Okay? You are looking at the pen and the
pen is coming from its own side. In the
second turn of the wheel, he
contradicted himself and said that
nothing comes from its own side. The
pen's coming from your mind from seeds
in your mind. Okay? And then in the
third turn of the wheel, the people who
were at the first turn of the wheel, who
then went to the second turn of the
wheel said, "Are you for real? I mean,
is that for real?" He said, "No, I was
just joking around." Uh, it's like half
coming from itself and half coming from
you. Don't Don't get all up tight, you
know. Everything's cool. Okay, got it.
Which one was correct?
Yeah, the second was correct. Why did he
teach the third one?
Mike, he was just trying to get people
otherwise they'll quit. They'll say, "I
quit. If pens don't come from
themselves, I quit. I'm going back to
New York. You know, I'm going to get a
advertising job or something easily.
This dharma stuff is weird.
Okay. Like that. Okay. He just wanted to
keep people from quitting. So he said,
"Yeah, yeah, you're right. I was
exaggerating."
Okay.
All right. So he turned the three turns
of the wheel for whom?
Three tracks. Three people of three
different capacities. He taught three
turns of the wheel. He's got two sets of
three here, right? Maybe we can get
through all of them in the next one
minute. I doubt it.
But we're not stopping.
So therefore, you taught the you taught
the path of the three janas, the three
the three vehicles, the three levels
like that. First one what? Hayana
meaning lower lower way. Okay. Then
mayana the greater way and then
the diamond way. Okay. The last two
overlap, right?
The sec the last two overlap cuz
right you know that I don't have to say
that. Okay.
You set forth a path
means the three realms. Okay. The three.
There's two ways to interpret it, but
I'll give you one. Okay. Uh desire
realm, form realm, and formless realm.
Desire realm, form realm, and formless
realm. We are in the desire realm. The
first diagnosis says because we are
attracted mainly to two things, food and
sex.
So I mean most people's attention I
heard somewhere that 60% of internet
traffic is pornography like that. And it
doesn't mean those people are evil. It
just means that they have this this is a
human desire. They have desire. We live
in desire of food. If you could eat on
the internet, that would probably be the
other 40%.
So,
you know, we that's who we are and we're
all like that. We all are attracted to
so that's a desirable and if you
overcome that, you reach a form real if
your meditation gets better and if it
gets better than that, you reach a
formless room. Okay, these are just
higher states of meditation. Okay, so
why did we mention that he is the Chipu
say
one and only friend. One and only
friend. Chipu means chip means one.
Chipu means one and only. Okay. He's the
only real friend. So you can have lots
of friends in this life, right? You can
have many many friends and they are
nice. It's good to have friends. I enjoy
all my friends immensely deeply. I have
a really good time with my friends. Me
and Dan and Doris, we sat at the Echo
Cafe on 68th and Thomas for 5 hours and
talked
saving books, saving the world, you
know. And I like my friends, okay? We
have friends. We all have friends.
So why does he call him the Buddha, the
only friend? He's the only one who can
really help you in a big big big way.
You can he can help you overcome death
itself. He can help you save. This is
the Buddha Lord Buddha only one and only
friend of all the beings in all three
realms. Okay, I'll do the last line
quick and I won't keep you
means
can mean possible. Sipa can mean samsara
as in coral
the wheel of life.
Uh but it can also mean uh realm. Look
at here it means super. Now he already
mentioned the concept which is the three
realms. Here he's repeating the three
realms. So if you're teaching it to a
class from Diamond Mountain, you can
give the second interpretation of three
realms the second time it comes which
means do you remember it?
Those who travel under the earth upon
the earth and who fly over the earth
meaning all creatures on this planet.
People are either
those little gophers that Earl feeds,
not realizing how nervous we are that
he'll get some kind of rabies and have
to go to hospital. Uh those are the
creatures that live under the dirt. And
then there's the creatures who walk on
the dirt, which are
us. And then there's the ones who fly.
So those are called the three the three
worlds. the the world under the earth,
the world on the earth, and the world
over the earth.
You are the teacher of all of those. All
three
high supreme teacher. Okay.
Okay. Three more words, we're finished.
Uh five dare to you to that teacher go
means in the three doors of expression.
This go means dora. Sue means I I I
praise you in my words or song. I praise
you with my body and in my heart I think
about how cool you are. Then that's go
ka means with respect express. And then
I get all this cult stuff about oh
people are bowing down in your class. Uh
this is tradition. This is 5,000 years
old. I'm sorry the Americans don't do
it. You know, maybe they should. Okay.
Uh it's a tradition that's 5,000 years
old. I did it to my teachers
uh my whole life and I enjoy it and I
like it and I think it's beautiful. In
China, people know how to treat a
teacher and it's very nice to be there
because they really know how to respect
a teacher and it's a big part of Chinese
culture. It's a beautiful part of
Chinese culture. We are like barbarians
compared to them. Anyway, I'm not gonna
rag on that.
Ha means uh respect with respect. Chel,
I bow I bow down to you. Okay. Even if
it's culty
uh that's uh you know the greatest uh
writer in Tibet unfortunately it's
bowing down to the Lord Buddha. Okay.
All right. Cool. So he starts his book
by bowing down to uh Lord Buddha. Okay.
The first verse is bowing down to Lord
Buddha.
Why is he doing that? If you tell me,
you get to go home. The retreats are
especially invested in this.
Generating merit.
Huh?
Yeah. It's good karma to bow down to
enlightened. That's true. He's
expressing that he's wisdom.
She says that we're she's he's buying
through wisdom and also it's showing
lineage for us. Lineage is very
important. Uh we we're very careful to
track our lineage and and now we have an
authentic lineage. We are not a bunch of
hippies out in the desert. We are the I
don't know 43rd generation of a lineage
which starts with
We say the lineage twice a month at
and we know the lineage and and now you
are the next holder of the lineage.
You're now my kids and you your kids
Dora's kids are my grandkids
and uh it goes back to lineage. So he's
he's honoring the lineage. Lineage
starts with Lord Buddha
and it comes up to us authentic. It's
authentic. It's been kept very very pure
and very cleanly. And even the Abid
Dharma lineage is very very pure and
amazing. Extraordinary. Okay. And you're
the next one. And if that means if you
don't take good notes
at at generation 44
uh after 2 and a half thousand years,
it's you guys who lost it, who broke it.
So no pressure.
Okay. Uh, and I encourage you to keep up
the clock. I encourage you to stream it
for the next 15 years. And I encourage
you
uh to to keep up with it. Okay. All
right. It's not hard. You can, the cool
thing about watching streaming is you
can you can eat stuff while you're
watching and you can put your feet up on
the table and you can take a pee break
and you come back and Michael's still
talking about the same.
I enjoy watching stuff streaming, you
know, cuz you can just relax, you know.
Here you have to sit like that, you
know, and at home you can put your
kitchen table.
So you don't have any excuse in the
modern world not to finish which is
started tonight. Okay? You have no
excuse. You should finish it.
You really should finish it. You can
help a lot of people with it.
Okay? Very valuable. Very helpful.
You're very lucky to get everything. All
right.